A Guide to the Bryan Family Papers, 1679-1943
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bryan Family Papers, 1679-1943
Library of Virginia
24882
5.5 cubic feet (13 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Do not serve Box 13, which contains originals of letters deemed too difficult to preserve. Xerox copies have been made and placed in the proper folders.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of John Stewart Bryan of Richmond, Virginia, 1952. Collection transferred from the administrative office of the Library to the Archives Division in May 1958.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joseph Bryan (1773-1812) of Savannah, Georgia, served as a congressman from 1803 to 1806, and became close friends with John Randolph (1773-1833) of Roanoke, Charlotte County, Virginia. He married Delia Forman (ca. 1788-1825) 5 April 1805, and they had 5 children including John Randolph Bryan (1806-1887). John Randolph Bryan's education was overseen by John Randolph. He served in the United States Navy from 1823 to 1831, then settled at Eagle Point in Gloucester County, Virginia. He later lived at Carysbrook in Fluvanna County, Virginia. Bryan married Elizabeth Tucker Coalter (1805-1856) 30 January 1830, and they had ten children, including Joseph Bryan (1845-1908). Joseph Bryan attended the University of Virginia from 1862 to 1863 and from 1865 to 1868. In between, he served as a member of the command of John S. Mosby (1833-1916) during the Civil War. He became a newspaper publisher in Richmond, Virginia, responsible for the Richmond Times, Richmond Times- Dispatch, and the Richmond News Leader. He also was a prominent businessman. Bryan lived at Brook Hill in Henrico County, Virginia, and at Laburnum in Richmond. He married Isobel Lamont Stewart (1847- 1910) 1 February 1871, and they had seven children, including John Stewart Bryan (1871-1944). John Stewart Bryan followed his father into newspaper publishing. He also served as president and chancellor of the College of William and Mary. He married Anne Eliza Tennant 4 June 1903 and they had three children.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1679-1943, of the Bryan family of Fluvanna, Gloucester, and Henrico Counties, and Richmond, Virginia, and Savannah, Georgia, consisting of Special Correspondence; General Correspondence; Genealogies; Business Records; Addresses, Essays, and Poems; and Miscellaneous. This collection has been microfilmed and is available on Misc. Reels 682-690.
Organization
Organized into the following six series: I. Special Correspondence. II. General Correspondence. III. Genealogies. IV. Business Records. V. Addresses, Essays, Poems and Diaries. VI. Miscellaneous.
Contents List
- Special Correspondence, 1780-1943 (Box 1)
  Inclues correspondence of John Randolph (1773-1833) of Roanoke with Joseph Bryan, John Randolph Bryan, Judith Randolph and others concerning national politics, Georgia politics, plantation life in Georgia, personal matters; correspondence between George Shea and Charles O'Conor regarding the imprisonment and trial of Jefferson Davis for which they were defense council; correspondence between John Stewart Bryan and Francis W. Hirst concerning U.S. and British politics and economics, Hirst's literary efforts, and personal matters; and miscellaneous correspondence containing essays written in the 1780s on banking and currency, correspondence to Charles Gottfried Paleske, Prussian Consul General in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, notes on the federal Constitution, Louisiana Territory, and a presidential election.
  - John Randolph of Roanoke, undated and 1791-1806 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John Randolph of Roanoke, 1806-1809 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John Randolph of Roanoke, 1810-1814 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Randolph of Roanoke, 1820-1831 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - George Shea-Charles O'Conor, undated and 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - George Shea-Charles O'Conor, 1867-1869 (1885) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hirst-Bryan, undated and 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1931-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1941, January-June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hirst-Bryan, 1941 July-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous-three essays and one letter on banking and currency, 1780, 1782, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous-papers concerning Charles Gottfried Paleske, Prussian Consul at Philadelphia, 1791-1799 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous-Notes on the Constitution of the United States (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous-Counterstatement, the Territory of Louisiana (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous-Election of the President (Box 1, Folder 19)
- General Correspondence, 1765-1937 (Box 2-5)
  Includes letters pertaining to family genealogy; naval career of John Randolph Bryan; John Randolph of Roanoke, including a biography and the removal of his remains to Hollywood Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia; Episcopal High School of Virginia near Alexandria, Virginia; St. Mary's College in Baltimore, Maryland; wreck of the Steamship Pulaski; education; slavery; Mosby's Rangers; Virginia politics before and after the Civil War; Richmond Howitzers; Hollywood Memorial Association; Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities; the John Marshall House; University of Virginia; the College of William and Mary; finances; politics; and family matters.
  - 1765-1818 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1821-1825 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1826-1827 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1830-1839 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1840-1846 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1846 July-1847 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1847 August-1849 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1850-1852 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1853-1854 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1855-1856 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1857-1859 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1860-1864 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1865-1869 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1870-1871 June (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1871 August-1872 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1873-1874 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1875-1877 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1878 January-June (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1878 October-1879 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1879 July-December (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1880 January-March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1880 April-June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1880 July-December (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1881 January-June (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1881 July-December (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1882 January-June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1882 July-December (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1883 January-June (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1883 July (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1883 August (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1883 September-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1884 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1885 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1886 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1887 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1888 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1889 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1890-1894 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1895-1899 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1900-1902 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1905-1906 September (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1906 October-1907 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1908 February-May (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1908 June (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1908 July 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1908 July 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1908 August (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1908 September-December (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1909-1910 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1910 May-1912 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1920-1925 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1926-1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Genealogies (Box 6-7)
  Includes genealogical notes and charts on the Bryan family; Randolph family; Bland family; Coalter family; Forman family; Pendarvis family; Bedon family; Screeven family; Williamson family; Hext family; Brannan family; Williston family; Hitchcock family; Goode family; Lyle family; Mosby family; Stuart family; Stewart family; and Beverly-Beverley family.
  - Randolph-Bland family (also box 12, folder 1) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Coalter family (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Coalter family (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Forman family (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pendarvis-Bedon-Screeven family (also box 12, folder 2) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bryan family-other branches (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bryan family-English origins (also box 12, folder 3) (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Bryan family-James Bryan (1752-1797) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11 - Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bryan family-charts, memoranda, etc. (Box 7, Folder 4-8)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1881-1894 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1896-1899 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1901-1902 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1903-1904 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1905-1906 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1907-1908 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Bryan family-correspondence re: genealogy, 1918-1932 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Business and Legal Papers, 1714-1909, undated (Box 8)
  Includes business papers of Daniel K. Stewart, John Stewart, and Joseph Bryan concerning their interests in the Sloss-Sheffield Works, American Locomotive Company, New York Equitable Life Association, Richmond and Charlottesville Turnpike, Brook Turnpike, Richmond and York River Railroad, Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Company, Richmond and Henrico Turnpike, Elberston Airline Railroad, Rosewell Railroad, Richmond and Danville Railroad, Georgia Pacific Railroad, Atlantic and Charlotte Airline Railroad; estate papers of John Stewart; bonds; agreements; powers of attorney; deeds; wills; suit papers; pardons; certificates; petitions; and minutes.
  - 1714-1829 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1830-1859 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1860-1879 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1880-1884 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1885-1886 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1889-1895 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1900-1909 and undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Addresses, Essays, Poems, 1679-1941 (Box 9)
  Includes poems; tombstone inscriptions; sermons; prayers; essays, addresses, and histories on Jamestown, College of William and Mary, Posey Page, John Randolph of Roanoke, statues of Virignia Confederate generals, African American suffrage, Bryan family during the Civil War, John Randolph Bryan's naval career, Eagle Point in Gloucester County, Virginia, Civil War balloons, Civil War experiences, banking in the South, and journalism. See also box 12, folders 4-5.
  - Addresses, Essays, Poems, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - 1679-1866 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1891-1899 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1903-1906 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1909 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1910-1919 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1925-1941 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1827-1892 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, Fragments and Envelopes (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous (see also box 12, folders 6-8) (Box 10-12)
  Includes hair locks; handkerchiefs; flowers; lists; grade cards; invitations and announcements; diaries; account books; vouchers; receipt books; Bryan Memoranda; and other miscellaneous items.
  - Confederate Roster, list of officers and men of the Albemarle Artillery who were captured this 9th day of April 1865 at Appomattox (accession 24918), Negative photostats (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Programs (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Political parties (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Printed miscellaneous material (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Printed miscellaneous material (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Thomas Green diaries (2), 1827-1829 - includes a letter, 31 May 1899, from Mary F. Stone to Joseph Bryan concerning diaries (Box 11)
  - Bryan Memoranda No. 1 - Joseph Bryan, Sr.; Hugh Bryan; Joseph Bryan, Second; Jonathan Bryan (Box 11)
  - Receipt book, 1886 (Box 11)
  - Joseph Bryan diary, 1888, includes three miscellaneous items, 1888, 1891, 1893 (Box 11)
  - Account book, 1887-1889 (Box 11)
  - Checks (vouchers) from Joseph Bryan, executor of John Stewart (Box 11)
  - Randolph-Bland family (box 6, folder 1) (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pendarvis-Bedon-Screeven family (box 6, folder 5) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Bryan family-English origins (box 6, folder 8) (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous-manuscript history of Jamestown (connected to the miscellaneous materials in boxes 9-10) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (connected to the miscellaneous materials in boxes 9-10), 1903-1924 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Maps (connected to the miscellaneous materials in boxes 9-10) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (connected to the miscellaneous materials in boxes 9-10) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Programs (connected to the miscellaneous materials in boxes 9-10) (Box 12, Folder 8)